[
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>read, live, come, teach, know, like, learn, wish, write</font> <br>আমার নাম মালতী । আমার ইস্কুলের নাম রাধানাথ বালিকা বিদ্যালয় । আমি ক্লাস ফাইভে পড়ি । আমাদের ক্লাসে তিরিশ জন মেয়ে । আমি বিদ্যালয়ের কাছেই একটা গ্রামে থাকি । ক্লাশের অনেকে ওখান থেকে আসে । আমাদের প্রধানশিক্ষিকা ইংরেজী পড়ান । আমি ইংরেজী ভালো জানিনা । কিন্তু আমার খুব ইংরেজী পড়তে ইচ্ছে হয় । আমাদের প্রধানশিক্ষিকা খুব ভালো পড়ান । ওনার জন্যই আমার ইংরেজী পড়তে ইচ্ছে হয় । লিখতেও আমায় শিখতে হবে ।",
    "answer":"My name is Malati. The name of my school is Radhanath Balika Vidyalaya. I read in class V. There are thirty students in our class. I live in a village near the school. Many students of my class come from there. Our headmistress teaches English. I do not know English well. But I like to learn English very much. Our headmistress teaches very well. Because of her only I wish to learn English. I have to learn to write too."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Study, go, play, want, get, become, fail, otherwise, stop, weak, say, need, speak, try</font> <br>আমি বাদশা । আমি ক্লাস সিক্সে পড়ি । আমার পড়াশোনা করতে ভালো লাগে না । আমি ইস্কুলে যাই খেলতে । বাবা চায়, আমি ভালো করে পড়ি । তাহলে ভালো চাকরি পাবো । আমি চাই খেলোয়াড় হতে । ক্লাসে ফেল করলে আমার পড়া বন্ধ । এখন একটু পড়ছি, নাহলে খেলা বন্ধ হয়ে যাবে । আমি ইংরেজীতে খুব কাঁচা । কিন্তু খেলার স্যার বলেছেন, আমার ইংরেজী জানা দরকার । নাহলে কথা বলা যাবে না । তাই এখন ইংরেজী পড়ার চেষ্টা করছি ।",
    "answer":"I am Badsha. I read in class six. I do not like to study. I go to school to play. Father wants that I study well. Then I shall get a good job. I want to become a player. If I fail in class, my study will be stopped. So I am reading a little, otherwise playing will be stopped. I am very weak in English. But the game-teacher has said that I need to learn English. Otherwise I shall not be able to speak English. So I am trying to read English now."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Want, know, teach, learn, love, get, chance, become, absent</font> <br>আমি সনজিদা ।  ক্লাস সেভেনে পড়ি ।  আমার বাবা চায় না,  আমি পড়ি ।  কিন্তু আমার মা চায় ।  আমার মা রোজ জানতে চায়, আমি কেমন পড়ছি ।  ক্লাসে কী পড়ানো হচ্ছে, জানে । মা চায়,  আমি যখন বড়ো হব,  তখন স্কুলে পড়াই ।  মা পড়তে ভালোবাসতো ।  কিন্তু সুযোগ পায় নি ।  তাই মা চায়, আমি পড়ি ।  আমিও কখনো ইস্কুল কামাই করি নি, আর করবও না ।",
    "answer":"I am Sanjida. I read in class seven. My father does not want that I study. But my mother wants so. My mother wants to know everyday how I am studying. She knows what is being taught in class. Mother wants that when I grow up, I shall teach in a school. Mother loved to study. But she did not get chance. So mother wants that I study. I too have never become absent in school, and shall not be either"
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Practise, stage, dance, sing, recite, run, jump, go, play, have fun, guest, secretary</font> <br>কাল আমাদের স্কুলে বার্ষিক অনুষ্ঠান । এখন রোজ তার প্র্যাকটিস চলছে । আমরা দুটো নাটক করছি । বড়রা করছে “অবাক জলপান” । এছাড়া আমরা নাচব, গাইব আর আবৃত্তি করব । সকালে হবে খেলার অনুষ্ঠান । তাতে আমরা দৌড়ব, হাইজাম্প আর লংজাম্প লাফাব আর কবাডি খেলব । যেমন-খুশী-সাজো খেলাটায় খুব মজা করব । শেষে থাকবে পুরষ্কার বিতরণ অনুষ্ঠান । প্রধান অতিথি হবেন আমাদের ইস্কুলের সম্পাদক মহাশয় ।",
    "answer":"There will be annual function at our school tomorrow. So we are having practice everyday. We are staging two dramas. The elder ones are doing “Abak Jalpan”. Other than that, we will dance, sing and recite. There will be sports programme in the morning. We shall run, play high-jump, long-jump and Kabaddi. We will have fun in the go-as-you-like game. There will be prize distribution ceremony in the end. The secretary of our school will be the chief guest."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Come back, ask, suffer from fever, lying down, tell, wash, sit, give food, eat, like, want, know, show, interest</font> <br>বাবা কাজ থেকে ফিরল । এসেই আমায় জিজ্ঞেস করলো, আমি কেমন আছি । কারণ কাল থেকে আমার জ্বর । দুদিন স্কুলে যেতে পারিনি । কেবল শুয়ে আছি সারাদিন । বাবাকে বললাম, কালকের চেয়ে ভালো আছি । বাবা তারপর হাতপা ধুয়ে বসলো । মা বাবাকে খেতে দিলো । আমাকেও দিলো । আমার খেতে ভালো লাগল না, কিন্তু খেলাম । বাবা জানতে চাইলো, আমি এখন কি কি পড়ছি । বাবা আমায় অঙ্ক দেখিয়ে দেয় । বাবা অঙ্কে খুব ভালো ছিলো । বাবার জন্যে আমারও অঙ্কে আগ্রহ আছে ।", 
    "answer":"Father had come back from work. As soon as he had come home, he had asked me how I had been. This is because I had been suffering from fever since yesterday. I could not go to school for two days. Whole day I had been lying down only. I had told father that I had been better than yesterday. Then father had sat down after washing his hands and legs. Mother had given father food to eat. And then she had given food to me also. I had not liked to eat, but had it anyway. Father had wanted to know what I had been reading then. Father shows me Mathematics. Father was good at Mathematics. I too have interest in Mathematics because of him only."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Match, experience, play, score, start, fault, catch, throw, take shot</font> <br>আজ আমাদের স্কুলে ফুটবল ম্যাচ । স্যারেদের সঙ্গে আমাদের খেলা । আমাদের দলে বেশ কজন ভালো খেলোয়াড় আছে, কিন্তু আমাদের অভিজ্ঞতা একেবারে নেই । যদিও স্যারেদের দলে অভিজ্ঞতা আছে, তাঁরা আবার বেশীক্ষণ খেলতে পারেন না । রেফারি হচ্ছেন আমাদের গেমটিচার । তিনি আবার আমাদের কোচও বটে । খেলা শুরু হল, আর স্যারেদের দল এক গোল দিয়ে দিলো । দোষ আমাদের গোলকিপারের, সে বল ভাল করে ধরতে পারেনি । পাঁচ মিনিটের মধ্যে আমাদের গোল । স্যারেদের দলের গোলকিপার বল ছুঁড়ল, আর শুভেন শট নিল । অমনি গোল । বিরতি পর্যন্ত খেলার ফল ড্র ।",
    "answer":"There is a football match at our school today. We will play against our teachers. Our team has some good players, but we have very little experience. Although the teachers’ team has experience, they can not play for long. Our game-teacher will be the referee. He is our coach as well. The match started, and the teachers’ team scored a goal. It was a fault of our goalkeeper; he could not catch the ball well. We then scored back in five minutes. As the goalkeeper of the teachers’ team threw the ball, Suven took a shot. And it was a goal. Till halftime the result of the match was draw"
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Play, start, try, keep pressure, come, get, come forward, walk, stand still, end</font> <br>বিরতির পর স্যারেরা নিজেদের অর্ধে খেলতে শুরু করলেন । আমাদের ছেলেরা বারবার চেষ্টা করল, কিন্তু গোল করতে পারলো না । স্যারেরাও আমাদের দিকে আসার চেষ্টা করলেন না । আমরা যথেষ্ট চাপ রাখলাম, কিন্তু গোল এল না ।  হঠাৎই একটা মিসপাস থেকে একজন স্যার বল পেয়ে গেলেন । আমাদের গোলকিপার এগিয়ে এলেও স্যার ওর মাথার ওপর দিয়ে ঠান্ডা মাথায় গোল করে গেলেন । স্যারেরা তারপর প্রায় হাঁটছিলেন, শেষে দাঁড়িয়ে পড়ছিলেন ।  তাই খেলা শেষ করে দেওয়া হল । শেষ পর্যন্ত খেলার ফল হল ২-১ ।",
    "answer":"After halftime the teachers started playing in their own half. Our boys tried time and again, but could not score. The teachers too did not try to come to our side as well. We kept lot of pressure, but still goal did not come. Then suddenly a teacher got the ball from a miss-pass. Even if our goalkeeper came forward, the teacher scored in cool head a goal over his head. Then the teachers were almost walking, and finally almost standing still. So the match was ended. The final score of the match was 2-1."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Do, work, rule, become, habit, sleep, wake up, brush, wash, bathe, wear, cut, sit, study, joy</font> <br>আমাদের রোজ নিয়ম করে কিছু কাজ করা উচিত । রোজ এক কাজ করলে তা অভ্যেস হয়ে যায় । তুমি যদি ১০টার সময় না ঘুমোও, সকালে কি করে উঠবে ? আমি রোজ নিয়ম করে সকালে ঘুম থেকে উঠি । দাঁত মাজি, মুখ ধুই, স্নান করি ।  তারপর পরিষ্কার জামাকাপড় পরি । খাবার সময় হাত ধুই, নিয়ম করে নখ কাটি । সকালে সন্ধ্যায় পড়তে বসি । রোজ বিকেলে খেলি - কোনোদিন ফুটবল, কোনোদিন ক্রিকেট বা কোনোদিন খো-খো । এতে আমাদের মন ভালো থাকে ।",
    "answer":"We should do some work everyday as a rule. If one does same work everyday, it becomes a habit. If you do not sleep at 10 PM, how do you wake up early in the morning? I get up early in the morning regularly. I brush my teeth, wash my face and bathe. Then I wear clean dress. I wash my hands before food and cut nails regularly. I sit to study every morning and evening. I play in the afternoon – someday football, someday cricket or someday kho-kho. Our minds remain joyful this way."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Read, type, habit, give, control, try, think, grow, ability, brain, get, choose, watch, hear, say, experience</font> <br>শুধু পাঠ্য বই আমরা কেন পড়ব ? গল্পের বই পড়ার অভ্যেস ভালো । আমাদের সেসব পড়তে হবে । এটা ভাষার ওপর বেশি দখল দেয় । চিন্তা করতে চেষ্টা কর, মনের মধ্যে ঠিক কি বাড়ে এতে । এতে মস্তিষ্কের ক্ষমতা বাড়ে । তাই আমরা সামনে যা পাবো তা-ই পড়ব, কিছু বাছব না । আর খুব লক্ষ্য করব । শুনব,  কে কী বলছে । এতে যদি আমাদের অভিজ্ঞতা না বাড়ে, আমাদের আরো বই পড়া উচিৎ ।",
    "answer":"Why shall we read only textbooks? The habit of reading story books is good. We have to read them. It gives more control on language. Try to think what exactly grows in mind because of this. Ability of the brain grows by this. So we will read whatever we get before us; we shall not choose. And we shall watch a lot. We shall hear what people are saying. And if our experience does not grow by this, we should read more books then."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Suddenly, meet, embrace, aunt, marriage ceremony, ask, submit, leave application, glad</font> <br>গতকাল রাস্তায় হঠাৎ অদিতির সঙ্গে দেখা । ও আমায় জড়িয়ে ধরে বললো,  ”এতদিন কোথায় ছিলি ?  স্কুলে আসিসনি কেন ? ”  আমি কিছু বলার আগেই আবার জানতে চাইলো,”কাল স্কুলে আসবি তো ? ” উত্তর দিলাম, ”হ্যাঁ আসবো” । তারপরে বললাম, ” আমার মাসীর বিয়ের জন্য আসতে পারিনি কদিন” । পরের দিন স্কুলে যেতেই আবার একই প্রশ্ন । স্কুলের শিক্ষিকারা আমাকে না আসার জন্য ছুটির দরখাস্ত জমা দিতে বললেন । আমি সঙ্গে নিয়ে গিয়েছিলাম, তাই দিয়ে দিলাম । দিদিমনি খুশী হলেন দরখাস্ত পেয়ে ।",
    "answer":"Yesterday I suddenly met Aditi on the road. She embraced me to say, “Where have you been for so long? Why didn’t you come to school?”. Before I said anything, she asked again, “Will you come to school tomorrow?” I answered, “Yes, I shall.”. Then I said, “I could not come to school for my aunt’s marriage ceremony.”. Next day as I went to school, I was asked the same question. The teachers of the school asked me to submit leave application. I took it with me, so submitted it. The teacher was glad getting the application."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Basket, lying, get, cry, look, find, immediately, pick, check up, inform, feed, save, keep, fill, hold</font> <br>একদিন রাস্তা দিয়ে যেতে যেতে তাপস দেখলো, একটা ঝুড়িতে কী যেন পড়ে আছে । সে কাছে গেল, আর কান্নার আওয়াজ শুনতে পেলো ভেতর থেকে । তাপস ভেতরে তাকিয়ে দেখল, দেখে একটা বাচ্চা । সঙ্গে সঙ্গে সে তাকে তুলে নিলো আর কাছের এক ডাক্তারের কাছে গেলো । ডাক্তার বাচ্চাটাকে ভালো করে দেখে জানালেন, ”এক্ষুণি একে দুধ খাওয়াতে হবে, নাহলে একে বাঁচানো যাবে না” । তাপস বাচ্চাটাকে নিয়ে সোজা বাড়ি চলে গেলো । ওর বোনের জন্য দুধ রাখা ছিল, তার থেকে কিছুটা নিয়ে ও বোতলে ভরলো । তারপর ওর মাকে বললো বাচ্চাটাকে ধরতে ।",
    "answer":"One day as Tapas was traveling, he saw something lying in a basket. He went near it, and heard a cry from inside it. Tapas looked inside, and found that it was a baby ! He picked it up immediately and took it to a doctor nearby. The doctor checked up the baby quite well and informed, “One has to feed it milk right now, otherwise it can not be saved.”. Tapas went home straight with the baby. Some milk was kept for his sister; He took some of it and filled a bottle with it. Then he asked his mother to hold the baby."
  },
  {
    "question":"<font color='#ED7745'>Taste, start, drink, understand, inform, police station, alone, aunt, fix, come up, suggest, work, keep looking, become angry, leave</font> <br>বাচ্চাটা মুখে দুধের স্বাদ পেল আর দুধ খেতে শুরু করে দিলো । তাপসের বাড়ির সবাই খুব খুশী । কিন্তু বাচ্চাটাকে নিয়ে কী করা হবে ? কেউ বুঝতে পারলো না । বাড়ির কেউ কেউ বললো, ”পুলিশে জানিয়ে আয় আগে” । তাপস একা গেল না, সঙ্গে এক কাকীমাকে নিলো । থানায় জানিয়ে এসে তাপসরা এবার বাচ্চাটার নাম ঠিক করতে বসলো । অনেক নাম এলো । শেষে তাপসের বোন একটা নাম বলল – কুট্টুস । সেই নামই দেওয়া হল বাচ্চাটার । এবার বাড়ির সবাই আর কোনো কাজ করে না, কেবল কুট্টুসের দিকেই তাকিয়ে থাকে । এতে তাপসের বোন কি রেগে যাবে না ? সে কেঁদে বলে, \"তোমরা কুট্টুসকে রেখে এসো রাস্তায়\"।",
    "answer":"The baby tasted milk in its mouth and started drinking it. Everybody in Tapas’ house was very happy. But what is to be done with the baby? Nobody could understand. Some from the family said, “Inform the police first.”. Tapas did not go alone, took an aunt with him. After informing at police station, Tapas and all sat to fix the name of the baby. Many names came up. Finally Tapas’ sister suggested a name – Kuttus. That name only was given to the baby. Now nobody from the house works anymore, everybody keeps looking at Kuttus only. Will not Tapas’ sister become angry at this? She says crying, “Leave Kuttus in the streets.”"
  }
]